I'm going to demonstrate how to use CytoCV to automate measurement of nuclear to cytoplasmic
intensity ratios for a fluorescently tagged protein.
This experiment requires a fluorescent protein that will define the location of the nucleus.
Here I'm using a nucleoporin protein that is tagged with a red fluorophore.
This red image shows the cell contour, which was obtained from the DIC image, and the outline
of the red nucleus.
The green images show my protein of interest, which is tagged with a green fluorophore and
accumulates in the nucleus in two distinct puncta.
Visually, we can see that this mutant on the bottom does not enter the nucleus as efficiently
as the wild type on top.
I'm now going to use CytoCV to calculate the difference in the nuclear versus cytoplasmic
intensity ratio of this green protein in individual cells for these two strains.
I have already signed in and uploaded two files, one each for wild type and mutant.
I will use the statistics plugin options to select the type of analysis that I want
to perform with these images.
First, I need to decide what types of cells to include in the analysis.
The cells for this experiment have been arrested in metaphase of mitosis and should therefore
be large-budded cell pairs, so I'll select the cell pairs only option.
Under signal quantification, I will choose nuclear cell pair intensity.
Under nucleus contour source, I need to choose the appropriate color option for this
experiment.
By selecting the red nucleus, measure green option, because I want to tell CytoCV to use
the red protein to make the nuclear contour, and then measure the intensity of the green
protein within that contour.
For the nucleus contour mode, I'm choosing the balanced option.
The signal for my nuclear protein can often be speckled, and I want all of those speckles
combined together into a single contour.
In the aggressive mode, CytoCV will split up the speckles into different contours.
I'll now turn off anything else selected that is irrelevant for what I want to analyze.
CytoCV can automatically identify and assign channel roles when sufficient metadata is
available.
Because my older source files do not contain the required metadata, I'm going to manually
set the channels by defining the order of the fluorescent images in my TIFF stack here.
Now I'll close this window and pre-process the files,
and then start the analysis.
I've now switched to a window in which the analysis has finished, and I can see the pairs
of cells that CytoCV has identified to analyze.
Below, I can visualize each individual cell pair and determine whether I want to keep that
cell for the analysis.
For this experiment, I want to analyze only cells in metaphase with a single nucleus
between the two cells.
In this first cell, there is a single red nuclear contour that spans the bud neck,
so this is the stage of cell that I want to quantitate.
I'm going to click through each cell and make sure that I want to keep it for the analysis.
All of these cells so far look good.
But here in cell 9, we have a problem.
The red contour doesn't match visually what I see as the red nuclear signal.
If I were to include this cell, the nucleus would be defined as larger than it actually is.
This cell is also problematic because there are two distinct red contours,
meaning the cell has already undergone anaphase.
To remove this cell from the analysis, I will click to the right of the cell and select
the delete cell option.
I'm going to delete cell 10 as well because it also has gone through anaphase.
Cell 11 looks fine.
And now I'm back to cell 1.
Now I'll go on to the mutant image.
Looking through these cells, all of them fit my criteria.
At this point, I'm ready to download the numerical data.
This table at the bottom has columns for all the types of analysis that CytoCV can
do, most of which we're ignoring for this experiment.
The numbers that are relevant to us are the ones at the very end of the table.
To export the data in a format that's easier for me to use,
I'll click Download Statistics.
I would like to view the data in Excel, so I'll select that option.
Most of these measurements are irrelevant to the current experiment,
and the ones at the bottom that pertain to my analysis are already checked.
To ensure that I will be downloading data for all the files
that I have analyzed in my session, I will click Edit Files, Select All.
And now I'm ready to download.
When I open this Excel file, I see the name of each image file on the left,
followed by all of the measurements and calculations
that I had previously selected.
Notice that cells 9 and 10 in the wild type image are missing.
This is because I deleted them.
By uploading many files with images similar to these and downloading the data,
I was able to generate a graph in GraphPad Prism
that displays the ratios for over 100 cells of both the wild type and the mutant.
The calculations show that the mutant protein of interest
has a lower nuclear to cytoplasmic intensity ratio than the wild type,
which was expected based on what I can see visually in these images.
The difference is highly significant.
So that's how CytoCV can be used
to calculate nuclear versus cytoplasmic intensities.
For other types of analysis, I would follow a similar process,
but choose different options in the statistics plug-in section.